A few months ago
منذ شهور قليلة
the Nobel Prize in physics
تم منح جائزة نوبل في الفيزياء
was awarded to two teams of astronomers
الى فريقين من علماء الفلك
for a discovery that has been hailed
عن كشف تم الاشادة به
as one of the most important
كأحد أهم
astronomical observations ever.
الاكشافات الفلكية على الاطلاق
And today, after briefly describing what they found,
واليوم ، بعد وصفهم المختصر لما اكتشفوه
I'm going to tell you about a highly controversial framework
سوف احكي لكم عن اطار عمل مثير للجدل جداً
for explaining their discovery,
لشرح اكتشافهم
namely the possibility
تحديداً اسمه الامكانية
that way beyond the Earth,
ذلك السبيل فيما وراء الأرض
the Milky Way and other distant galaxies,
الطريق اللبني والمجرات البعيدة الاخرى
we may find that our universe
من الممكن ان نجد أن كوننا
is not the only universe,
ليس هو الكون الوحيد
but is instead
ولكنه بدلاً من ذلك
part of a vast complex of universes
جزء من اكوان معقدة كبيرة
that we call the multiverse.
ما نطلق عليه متعدد الاكوان
Now the idea of a multiverse is a strange one.
الأن الفكرة من تعدد الاكوان هي فكرة غريبة
I mean, most of us were raised to believe
أعني ، معظمنا تربي ليعتقد
that the word "universe" means everything.
ان كلمة "كون" تعني كل شيئ
And I say most of us with forethought,
و أقول ان معظمنا مع بعض الدراسة
as my four-year-old daughter has heard me speak of these ideas since she was born.
مثل ابنتي ذات الاربعة اعوام تسمعني اتحدث عن هذه الافكار منذ ولادتها
And last year I was holding her
والعام الماضي كنت احملها
and I said, "Sophia,
وقلت ، "صوفيا ،
I love you more than anything in the universe."
احبك اكثر من اي شيئ في الكون"
And she turned to me and said, "Daddy,
وتحولت الي وقالت "أبي،
universe or multiverse?"
الكون ام الكون المتعدد
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But barring such an anomalous upbringing,
ولكن منعاً لمثل تلك هذه التنشئة الشاذة
it is strange to imagine
فإنه من الغريب ان نتخيل
other realms separate from ours,
عوالم اخرى تنفصل عنا
most with fundamentally different features,
معظمها بملامح مخنلفة أساساً
that would rightly be called universes of their own.
بحيث يمكن ان نطلق عليها مباشرة اسم أكوان بنفسها
And yet,
وحتى الآن
speculative though the idea surely is,
التضارب خلال الفكرة هو بالتأكيد
I aim to convince you
انني اهدف الى اقناعكم
that there's reason for taking it seriously,
ان هناك سبباً لأخذ الموضوع على محمل الجد
as it just might be right.
كما لوكانت صحيحة
I'm going to tell the story of the multiverse in three parts.
سأسرد عليكم قصة عن الاكوان المتعددة في ثلاثة اجزاء
In part one,
في الجزء الاول
I'm going to describe those Nobel Prize-winning results
سأقوم بوصف نتائج الفوز بجائزة نوبل تلك
and to highlight a profound mystery
و القاء الضوء على الغموض العميق
which those results revealed.
الذي ابرزته تلك النتائج
In part two,
في الجزء الثاني
I'll offer a solution to that mystery.
سأعرض حلاً لهذا الغموض
It's based on an approach called string theory,
يبنى على نهج يسمى نظرية الأوتار
and that's where the idea of the multiverse
وهناك حيث ستبرز فكرة
will come into the story.
الأكوان المتعددة في القصة
Finally, in part three,
وأخيراً ، في الجزء الثالث
I'm going to describe a cosmological theory
سوف اصف نظرية الكوزمولوجي
called inflation,
تدعى التضخم
which will pull all the pieces of the story together.
والتي ستقوم بسحب كل قطع القصة معاً
Okay, part one starts back in 1929
حسناً ، يبدأ الجزء الأول في الماضي في 1929
when the great astronomer Edwin Hubble
عندما أدرك الفلكي العظيم ادوين هابل
realized that the distant galaxies
ان المجرات البعيدة
were all rushing away from us,
تتباعد في عجلة عنا
establishing that space itself is stretching,
بما يؤسس ان الفضاء نفسه يتمدد
it's expanding.
يتوسع
Now this was revolutionary.
الآن هذا كان ثورياً
The prevailing wisdom was that on the largest of scales
كانت الحكم السائدة على نطاق واسع
the universe was static.
ان الكون ساكن
But even so,
ولكن مع ذلك حتى
there was one thing that everyone was certain of:
كان هناك شيئاً ما كان الجميع متأكدون منه
The expansion must be slowing down.
ان التوسع يجب ان يتباطأ
That, much as the gravitational pull of the Earth
حيث ، بقدر ما ان الجاذبية تسحب الارض
slows the ascent of an apple tossed upward,
تبطيء صعود تفاحة القيت لأعلى
the gravitational pull
فان سحب الجاذبية
of each galaxy on every other
لكل مجرة عن الاخرى
must be slowing
يجب ان يبطئ
the expansion of space.
التوسع في الفضاء
Now let's fast-forward to the 1990s
والآن لنتقدم سريعاً نحو التسعينات
when those two teams of astronomers
عندما قام هذان الفلكيان
I mentioned at the outset
اللذان ذكرتهما في البداية
were inspired by this reasoning
بعد الهامهما بهذا المنطق
to measure the rate
لقياس المعدل
at which the expansion has been slowing.
الذي به يتم بتاطؤ هذا التوسع
And they did this
وقاموا بالآتي
by painstaking observations
بملاحظة دؤوبة
of numerous distant galaxies,
للمجرات البعيدة الكثيرة
allowing them to chart
بما يسمح لهم برسم خريطة
how the expansion rate has changed over time.
عن كيف ان معدل التوسع قد تغير بمرور الوقت
Here's the surprise:
وهنا كانت المفاجأة
They found that the expansion is not slowing down.
لقد وجدوا ان التوسع لم يكن يتباطأ
Instead they found that it's speeding up,
ولكنهم وجدوا انه يتسارع
going faster and faster.
أسرع فأسرع
That's like tossing an apple upward
وهذا مثل قذف تفاحة للأعلى
and it goes up faster and faster.
وهي تذهب الى الاعلى اسرع فأسرع
Now if you saw an apple do that,
الآن اذا رأيت تفاحة تفعل ذلك
you'd want to know why.
يتوجب عليك معرفة السبب
What's pushing on it?
ما الذي يدفعها
Similarly, the astronomers' results
نفس الشيئ ، ان نتائج الفلكيين
are surely well-deserving of the Nobel Prize,
ادت بالتأكيد انهم يستحقون جائزة نوبل بجدارة
but they raised an analogous question.
ولكنهم طرحوا سؤالاً مماثلاً
What force is driving all galaxies
ما هي القوة التي تسوق كل المجرات
to rush away from every other
للذهاب بعيداً بسرعة عن بعضها البعض
at an ever-quickening speed?
بطريقة متسارعة
Well the most promising answer
حسناً ان الاجابة الواعدة
comes from an old idea of Einstein's.
تأتي من فكرة قديمة لأينشتاين
You see, we are all used to gravity
كما ترون ، فقد تعودنا ان الجاذبية
being a force that does one thing,
هي قوة تفعل شيئاً واحداً فقط
pulls objects together.
تسحب الاشياء مع بعضها
But in Einstein's theory of gravity,
ولكن نظرية اينشتاين عن الجاذبية
his general theory of relativity,
نظريته العامة عن النسبية
gravity can also push things apart.
الجاذبية يمكنها كذلك دفع الاشياء عن بعضها
How? Well according to Einstein's math,
كيف ؟ حسناً وطبقاً لحسابات اينشتاين
if space is uniformly filled
لو امتلأء الفراغ بشكل موحد
with an invisible energy,
بطاقة غير مرئية
sort of like a uniform, invisible mist,
نوعاً ما مثل الضباب غير المرئي المنتظم
then the gravity generated by that mist
اذن فالجاذبية تولدت من ذلك الضباب
would be repulsive,
فهذا منفرة
repulsive gravity,
جاذبية منفرة
which is just what we need to explain the observations.
وهذا بالضبط مانحتاجه لتفسير الملاحظات
Because the repulsive gravity
لأن الجاذبية المنفرة
of an invisible energy in space --
للطاقة غير المرئية في الفضاء
we now call it dark energy,
الآن ندعوها الطاقة المظلمة
but I've made it smokey white here so you can see it --
ولكنني جعلتها ابيض مدخن هنا حتى تتمكنوا من رؤيتها
its repulsive gravity
طاقتها المنفرة
would cause each galaxy to push against every other,
ستتسبب في دفع كل مجرة مقابل الاخرى
driving expansion to speed up,
تقود التوسع للتسارع
not slow down.
وليس للتباطؤ
And this explanation
وهذا التفسير
represents great progress.
يمثل تقدماً عظيماً
But I promised you a mystery
ولكنني اعدكم بالغموض
here in part one.
هذا هو الجزء الاول
Here it is.
هذا هو
When the astronomers worked out
عندما قام الفلكيان بالعمل على
how much of this dark energy
كم من هذه الطاقة المظلمة
must be infusing space
يجب ان يغرس في الفضاء
to account for the cosmic speed up,
يجب حسابه للسرعة الكونية
look at what they found.
انظروا ماذا وجدوا
This number is small.
الرقم صغير
Expressed in the relevant unit,
معبراً عنه بالوحدات المتعلقة
it is spectacularly small.
هو صغير بصورة مذهلة
And the mystery is to explain this peculiar number.
والغموض انه لشرح هذا الرقم الغريب
We want this number
نريد ان يخرج هذا الرقم
to emerge from the laws of physics,
من قوانين الفيزياء
but so far no one has found a way to do that.
ولكن حتى الآن لم يجد اي احد وسيلة لذلك
Now you might wonder,
والآن محتمل ان تتعجب
should you care?
هل تهتم
Maybe explaining this number
ربما شرح هذا الرقم
is just a technical issue,
مجرد مسألة تقنية
a technical detail of interest to experts,
تفاصيل تقنية تهم الخبراء
but of no relevance to anybody else.
ولكن غير متعلق بأي احد آخر
Well it surely is a technical detail,
حسناً انها بالتأكيد تفاصيل تقنية
but some details really matter.
ولكن بعض التفاصيل حقاً تهم
Some details provide
بعض التفاصيل تعطي
windows into uncharted realms of reality,
نافذة الى مملكة الواقع المجهولة
and this peculiar number may be doing just that,
وهذ الرقم الغريب من الممكن ان يفعل ذلك
as the only approach that's so far made headway to explain it
وأحرز المدخل الوحيد لذلك حتى الآن تقدماً لتفسير ذلك
invokes the possibility of other universes --
يستدعي احتمال وجود أكوان أخرى
an idea that naturally emerges from string theory,
فكرة انها بالطبيعة تخرج من نظرية السلسلة
which takes me to part two: string theory.
والذي يأخذني الى الجزء الأول : نظرية الأوتار
So hold the mystery of the dark energy
أذن مع الاحتفاظ بغموض الطاقة المبهمة
in the back of your mind
في خلفية عقلكم
as I now go on to tell you
حيث سأقوم بإخباركم ب
three key things about string theory.
ثلاثة أشياء رئيسية عن نظرية الأوتار
First off, what is it?
أولاً , ما هي؟
Well it's an approach to realize Einstein's dream
حسناً فهذا مدخل لادراك حلم اينشتين
of a unified theory of physics,
عن النظرية الموحدة للفيزياء
a single overarching framework
اطار عمل شامل وحيد
that would be able to describe
من الممكن وصف
all the forces at work in the universe.
كل القوى اثناء عملها في الكون
And the central idea of string theory
والفكرة المركزية عن نظرية الأوتار
is quite straightforward.
في الواقع فكرة مباشرة
It says that if you examine
تقول انك اذا اختبرت
any piece of matter ever more finely,
اي جزء من مادة بدقة متناهية
at first you'll find molecules
في البداية سوف تجد جزيئات
and then you'll find atoms and subatomic particles.
ومن ثم سوف تجد ذرات و جسيمات ذرية
But the theory says that if you could probe smaller,
ولكن النظرية تقول انك لو استطعت التفتيت الى اصغر
much smaller than we can with existing technology,
اصغر بكثير عما نستطيعه بالتقنيات الحالية
you'd find something else inside these particles --
فقد تجد شيئاً آخر داخل هذه الجسيمات
a little tiny vibrating filament of energy,
خيطاً رفيعاً يهتز من الطاقة
a little tiny vibrating string.
أوتار دقيقة تهتز
And just like the strings on a violin,
بالضبط شبه الخيوط الموجودة على الكمان
they can vibrate in different patterns
يمكنها الاهتزاز في قوالب مختلفة
producing different musical notes.
منتجةً نوتات موسيقية مختلفة
These little fundamental strings,
هذه الخيوط الأساسية الصغيرة
when they vibrate in different patterns,
عندما تهتز في انماط مختلفة
they produce different kinds of particles --
تنتج انواع مختلفة من الجسيمات
so electrons, quarks, neutrinos, photons,
منها الالكترونات ، الكواراكات ، النيوترونات ، الفوتونات
all other particles
كل الجسيمات الاخرى
would be united into a single framework,
ستتحد في اطار وحيد
as they would all arise from vibrating strings.
بينما تنشأ جميعها من الأوتار المهتزة
It's a compelling picture,
انها صورة قاهرة
a kind of cosmic symphony,
نوع من السيمفونية الكونية
where all the richness
حيث كل الثراء
that we see in the world around us
الذي نراه في العالم حولنا
emerges from the music
يخرج من الموسيقى
that these little, tiny strings can play.
هذه الاشياء الدقيقة والصغيرة تستطيع ان تلعب موسيقى
But there's a cost
ولكن هناك ثمن
to this elegant unification,
لهذا التوحد الانيق
because years of research
لأن أعواماً من الابحاث
have shown that the math of string theory doesn't quite work.
اظهرت ان حساب نظرية الأوتار لا يتم بالضبط
It has internal inconsistencies,
فهناك عدم تناسق موجود
unless we allow
الا اذا اعطينا
for something wholly unfamiliar --
لبعض الاشياء غير المألوفة كلياً
extra dimensions of space.
ابعاداً اضافية في الفضاء
That is, we all know about the usual three dimensions of space.
هذا هو ، نحن جميعا نعلم عن الابعاد الثلاثة للفضاء
And you can think about those
ويمكنكم التفكير في هذه
as height, width and depth.
على انها الارتفاع , العرض والعمق
But string theory says that, on fantastically small scales,
ولكن نظرية الأوتار تقول انه على مقاييس صغيرة بطريقة خيالية
there are additional dimensions
هناك ابعاداً اضافية
crumpled to a tiny size so small
تتكوم في حجم صغير دقيق
that we have not detected them.
لم نتمكن من اكتشافه
But even though the dimensions are hidden,
ولكن بالرغم من ان الابعاد مختبئة
they would have an impact on things that we can observe
ولكن لديها تأثير على الاشياء نستطيع ملاحظته
because the shape of the extra dimensions
لأن شكل الابعاد الاضافية
constrains how the strings can vibrate.
يقيد كيفية قدرة الأوتار على الاهتزاز
And in string theory,
وفي نظرية الأوتار
vibration determines everything.
الاهتزاز يحدد كل شيئ
So particle masses, the strengths of forces,
لذلك فإن كميات الجسيمات ، ونقاط قوتها
and most importantly, the amount of dark energy
والأكثر أهمية ، كمية الطاقة المظلمة
would be determined
يتم تحديدها
by the shape of the extra dimensions.
بشكل الابعاد الاضافية
So if we knew the shape of the extra dimensions,
لذا لو علمنا شكل الابعاد الاضافية
we should be able to calculate these features,
سوف نتمكن من حساب هذه الميزات
calculate the amount of dark energy.
حساب كمية الطاقة المظلمة
The challenge
التحدي
is we don't know
لو لم نعلم
the shape of the extra dimensions.
هو شكل الابعاد الاضافية
All we have
كل ما نعلمه
is a list of candidate shapes
هو قائمة بالاشكال المرشحة
allowed by the math.
اتيحت بالحساب
Now when these ideas were first developed,
الآن وعندما تم تطوير هذه الافكار
there were only about five different candidate shapes,
كان هناك فقط حوالي خمسة أشكال مرشحة
so you can imagine
لذلك يمكنكم تخيلها
analyzing them one-by-one
وتحليلها واحدة واحدة
to determine if any yield
لتحديد اي محصلة
the physical features we observe.
سوف تنجم عن الملامح الفيزيائية
But over time the list grew
ولكن بمرور الوقت نمت هذه القائمة
as researchers found other candidate shapes.
لأن الباحثون وجدوا اشكالاً مرشحة أخرى
From five, the number grew into the hundreds and then the thousands --
من خمسة ، نما العدد الى المئات ثم الآلاف
A large, but still manageable, collection to analyze,
كبير ولكنها مجموعة مازال تحت السيطرة ويمكن تحليلها
since after all,
وبعد كل شيئ
graduate students need something to do.
فإن الطلاب المتخرجين يحتاجون لشيئ يعملونه
But then the list continued to grow
ولكن القائمة استمرت في النمو
into the millions and the billions, until today.
الى ملايين و بلايين حتى اليوم
The list of candidate shapes
ارتفعت قائمة الاشكال المرشحة
has soared to about 10 to the 500.
الى حوالي 10 الى 500
So, what to do?
اذن ما العمل ؟
Well some researchers lost heart,
بعض الباحثين فقد قلبه
concluding that was so many candidate shapes for the extra dimensions,
خالصاً الى انه مع هذا العدد من الاشكال المرشحة للابعاد الاضافية
each giving rise to different physical features,
فان كل ارتفاع للملامح الفيزيائية المختلفة
string theory would never make
فلن يمكن لنظرية الأوتار
definitive, testable predictions.
بالتحديد تنبوءات قابلة للاختبار
But others turned this issue on its head,
ولكن أخرون حولوا هذه المسألة في عقولهم
taking us to the possibility of a multiverse.
آخذينا الى احتمالية الاكوان المتعددة
Here's the idea.
هنا الفكرة
Maybe each of these shapes is on an equal footing with every other.
من المحتمل ان تكون هذه الاشكال على قدم المساواة مع كل الآخرين
Each is as real as every other,
الكل حقيقي مثل كل الآخرين
in the sense
بمعنى
that there are many universes,
ان هناك اكوان كثيرة
each with a different shape, for the extra dimensions.
كل منها له شكل للأبعاد الاضافية
And this radical proposal
وهذا العرض الجذري
has a profound impact on this mystery:
له تأثير عميق على الغموض
the amount of dark energy revealed by the Nobel Prize-winning results.
تم اكتشاف حجم الطاقة المظلمة بواسطة نتائج رابحي جائزة نوبل
Because you see,
لأنك ترى
if there are other universes,
لو كان هناك اكوان اخرى
and if those universes
ولو كان هذه الاكوان
each have, say, a different shape for the extra dimensions,
كل منها ، افترض ، لديه شكل مختلف من الابعاد الاضافية
then the physical features of each universe will be different,
اذن فالملامح الفيزيائية لكل كون سيكون مختلفاً
and in particular,
وبالخصوص
the amount of dark energy in each universe
كمية الطاقة المظلمة في كل كون
will be different.
ستكون مختلفة
Which means that the mystery
بما يعني ان الغموض
of explaining the amount of dark energy we've now measured
في تفسير كمية الطاقة المظلمة التي قمنا بقياسها
would take on a wholly different character.
ستؤخذ على شكل مختلف كلياً
In this context,
في هذا السياق
the laws of physics can't explain one number for the dark energy
قوانين الفيزياء لا تستطيع تفسير رقم واحد من الطاقة المظلمة
because there isn't just one number,
لأنه لا يوجد رقم واحد
there are many numbers.
هناك العديد من الارقام
Which means
بما يعني
we have been asking the wrong question.
اننا قد سألنا السؤال الخطأ
It's that the right question to ask is,
هل السؤال الصحيح هو
why do we humans find ourselves in a universe
لمذا نجد انفسنا كبشر في كون
with a particular amount of dark energy we've measured
بكمية من الطاقة المظلمة قد قسناها
instead of any of the other possibilities
بدلاً من أي من الاحتمالات الاخرى
that are out there?
الموجودة هناك
And that's a question on which we can make headway.
وذلك سؤال يمكننا من المضي قدماً
Because those universes
لأن هذه الأكوان
that have much more dark energy than ours,
التي لديها طاقة مظلمة اكثر من كوننا
whenever matter tries to clump into galaxies,
حينما تحاول هذه المادة التكتل في المجرات
the repulsive push of the dark energy is so strong
فإن الدفع المنفر للطاقة المظلمة يكون قوياً
that it blows the clump apart
بالقدر الذي ينفخ به الكتلة الى اجزاء
and galaxies don't form.
ولا تتكون المجرات
And in those universes that have much less dark energy,
وفي هذه المجرات التي لديها طاقة مظلمة اقل بكثير
well they collapse back on themselves so quickly
فإنها تنهار على نفسها بسرعة
that, again, galaxies don't form.
وهنا ايضاً لا تتكون المجرات
And without galaxies, there are no stars, no planets
وبدون المجرات لا توجد نجوم ولا كواكب
and no chance
ولا توجد فرصة
for our form of life
لأي شكل من أشكال الحياة
to exist in those other universes.
للوجود في تلك الأكوان
So we find ourselves in a universe
لذا نجد انفسنا في كون ما
with the particular amount of dark energy we've measured
مع كمية محددة من الطاقة المظلمة التي قمنا بقياسها
simply because our universe has conditions
ببساطة لأن كوننا لديه ظروف
hospitable to our form of life.
مضيافة لشكل الحياة التي نحياها
And that would be that.
وذلك من شأنه ان
Mystery solved,
يُحل الغموض
multiverse found.
تم ايجاد الاكوان المتعددة
Now some find this explanation unsatisfying.
والآن هناك البعض الذين لا يجدون هذا التفسير مرضياً
We're used to physics
لقد استخدمنا الفيزياء
giving us definitive explanations for the features we observe.
لتعطينا تفسيراً محدداً للملامح التي رصدناها
But the point is,
ولكن الموضوع هو
if the feature you're observing
لو ان الملامح التي ترصدها
can and does take on
يمكن وبالفعل تأخذ
a wide variety of different values
تشكيلة واسعة من القيم المختلفة
across the wider landscape of reality,
عبر مساحة اوسع من الحقيقة
then thinking one explanation
اذن التفكير في تفسير واحد
for a particular value
لقيمة معينة
is simply misguided.
هو ببساطة مضلل
An early example
وفي مثال متقدم
comes from the great astronomer Johannes Kepler
يأتي من الفلكي العظيم يوهانس كيبلر
who was obsessed with understanding
والذي كان مهووساً بفهم
a different number --
رقم مختلف
why the Sun is 93 million miles away from the Earth.
لماذا تبعد الشمس 93 مليون ميل من الارض
And he worked for decades trying to explain this number,
وعمل لعقود محاولاً تفسير هذا الرقم
but he never succeeded, and we know why.
ولكنه لم ينجح ونحن نعلم لماذا
Kepler was asking
كيبلر كان يسأل
the wrong question.
السؤال الخطأ
We now know that there are many planets
نحن نعلم الآن ان هناك الكثير من الكواكب
at a wide variety of different distances from their host stars.
على ابعاد متنوعة مختلفة من نجومها المضيفة
So hoping that the laws of physics
لذلك مع الامل بان قوانين الفيزياء
will explain one particular number, 93 million miles,
سوف تشرح رقم معين ، 93 مليون ميل
well that is simply wrongheaded.
حسناً فإن هذا ببساطة توجه خاطئ
Instead the right question to ask is,
بدلاً من ذلك فإن السؤال الصحيح الذي نسأله هو :
why do we humans find ourselves on a planet
لماذا نجد انفسنا نحن البشر على كوكب
at this particular distance,
على هذه المسافة المحددة
instead of any of the other possibilities?
بدلا من الاحتمالات الأخرى؟
And again, that's a question we can answer.
وايضاً ، هذا سؤال نستطيع الاجابة عنه
Those planets which are much closer to a star like the Sun
تلك الكواكب التي تكون اقرب كثيراً من نجم مثل الشمس
would be so hot
ستكون حارة جداً
that our form of life wouldn't exist.
بالشكل الذي لا توجد معه شكل الحياة التي نعيشها
And those planets that are much farther away from the star,
وتلك الكواكب التي تبعد كثيراً عن الشمس
well they're so cold
تكون باردة جداً
that, again, our form of life would not take hold.
بنفس القدر الذي لا تتحمله شكل الحياة التي نحياها
So we find ourselves
لذا فقد وجدنا انفسنا
on a planet at this particular distance
على كوكب على هذه المسافة المحددة
simply because it yields conditions
لانها ببساطة تتحصل على ظروف
vital to our form of life.
حيوية لشكل الحياة التي نحياها
And when it comes to planets and their distances,
وعندما تأتي الى كواكب ومسافاتها
this clearly is the right kind of reasoning.
فهذا بوضوح هو النوع الصحيح من التبرير
The point is,
والهدف هو
when it comes to universes and the dark energy that they contain,
عندما نأتي الى الاكوان والطاقة المظلمة التي تحتويها
it may also be the right kind of reasoning.
فإنه من الممكن كذلك ان يكون النوع الصحيح من التبرير
One key difference, of course,
هناك اختلاف جوهري ، بالطبع
is we know that there are other planets out there,
وهو اننا نعلم ان هناك كواكب اخرى
but so far I've only speculated on the possibility
ولكن الى الآن فقد تكهنت احتمالية
that there might be other universes.
ان هناك من المحتمل ان يكون اكوان اخرى
So to pull it all together,
ولوضع الجميع سوياً
we need a mechanism
نحتاج الى آلية
that can actually generate other universes.
تستطيع بالفعل توليد اكوان اخرى
And that takes me to my final part, part three.
وهذا يأخذني الى الجزء الاخير ، الجزء الثالث
Because such a mechanism has been found
لأن مثل هذه الالية قد تم ايجادها
by cosmologists trying to understand the Big Bang.
بواسطة العلماء الكونيين محاولين فهم الانفجار الكبير
You see, when we speak of the Big Bang,
هل ترى ، عندما نتحدث عن الانفجار الكبير
we often have an image
فغالباً يكون لدينا صورة
of a kind of cosmic explosion
عن نوع من الانفجار الكوني
that created our universe
الذي خلق كوننا
and set space rushing outward.
ووضع الفضاء في حالة خروج متسارع
But there's a little secret.
ولكن هناك سر صغير
The Big Bang leaves out something pretty important,
لقد ترك الانفجار الكبير شيئاً مهماً بعض الشيء
the Bang.
الانفجار
It tells us how the universe evolved after the Bang,
فهو يخبرنا كيف ان الكون تطور بعد الانفجار
but gives us no insight
ولكنه لا يعطينا نظرة متبصرة
into what would have powered the Bang itself.
عما قد يكون منح القوة للانفجار نفسه
And this gap was finally filled
وقد تم ملء هذه الفجوة في النهاية
by an enhanced version of the Big Bang theory.
بواسطة نسخة محسنة عن نظرية الانفجار الكبير
It's called inflationary cosmology,
وهو ما يدعى التمدد الكوني
which identified a particular kind of fuel
التي تحدد نوعاً معيناً من الوقود
that would naturally generate
التي بالطبع ولَد
an outward rush of space.
التسارع الخارجي للفضاء
The fuel is based on something called a quantum field,
يقوم الوقود على شيئ يدعى الحقل الكمي
but the only detail that matters for us
ولكن التفصيلة الوحيدة التي تهمنا
is that this fuel proves to be so efficient
هي ان هذا الوقود اثبت من الكفاءة
that it's virtually impossible
التي من المحتمل افتراضياً
to use it all up,
استخدامها جميعاً
which means in the inflationary theory,
بمعنى في نظرية التمدد
the Big Bang giving rise to our universe
قد اعطى الانفجار الكبير البداية لكوننا
is likely not a one-time event.
وهو ما لا يشبه حدث المرة الواحدة
Instead the fuel not only generated our Big Bang,
بدلاً عن ذلك فان الوقود لم يولد فقط الانفجار الكبير
but it would also generate countless other Big Bangs,
ولكنه ولد كذلك انفجارات كبيرة اخرى لا تعد ولا تحصى
each giving rise to its own separate universe
كل منها اعطى النشوء لكونها المنفصل
with our universe becoming but one bubble
مع كوننا الذي اصبح فقاعة واحدة
in a grand cosmic bubble bath of universes.
في حمام الفقاعات الكبير للاكوان
And now, when we meld this with string theory,
والآن ، عندما صهرنا ذلك مع نظرية الأوتار
here's the picture we're led to.
هاهي الصورة التي قادتنا اليها
Each of these universes has extra dimensions.
كل من هذه الاكوان له ابعاداً اضافية
The extra dimensions take on a wide variety of different shapes.
الابعاد الاضافية تتشكل في اشكال متنوعة ومختلفة
The different shapes yield different physical features.
الاشكال المختلفة ينتج عنها ملامح فيزيائية مختلفة
And we find ourselves in one universe instead of another
ونجد انفسنا في كون ما بدلاً من كون اخر
simply because it's only in our universe
ببساطة لأنه فقط في كوننا
that the physical features, like the amount of dark energy,
هذه هي الملامح الفيزيائية مثل كمية الطاقة المظلمة
are right for our form of life to take hold.
هي مناسبة لشكلة الحياة التي نحياها
And this is the compelling but highly controversial picture
وهذه هي الصورة القاهرة المثيرة للجدل
of the wider cosmos
للاكوان الاوسع
that cutting-edge observation and theory
المتطورة عن الرصد و االنظرية
have now led us to seriously consider.
قد قادتنا الى اعتبار خطير
One big remaining question, of course, is,
تبقى سؤال واحد كبير ، بالطبع ، هو
could we ever confirm
هل من المحتمل ان نتأكد
the existence of other universes?
من وجود اكواناً أخرى ؟
Well let me describe
حسناً ، دعوني اشرح
one way that might one day happen.
عما يمكن ان كون قد حدث في يوم ما
The inflationary theory
نظرية التمدد
already has strong observational support.
لها ما يدعمها بقوة من الملاحظات
Because the theory predicts
لأن النظرية تتنباً
that the Big Bang would have been so intense
ان الانفجار الكبير من الممكن ان يكون شديداً
that as space rapidly expanded,
بحيث ان الفضاء قد تمدد بسرعة
tiny quantum jitters from the micro world
بحيث ان لوكان لدينا كمية من العالم الدقيق
would have been stretched out to the macro world,
قد يكون تمدده خارجاً الى العالم الكبير
yielding a distinctive fingerprint,
منتجاً اثار بصمات مميزة
a pattern of slightly hotter spots and slightly colder spots,
نمط من نقاط اسخن قليلاً و نقاط ابرد قليلاً
across space,
عبر الفضاء
which powerful telescopes have now observed.
والتي تم رصدها بواسطة التليسكوبات القوية الآن
Going further, if there are other universes,
وبالذهاب بعيداً ، لو كان هناك أكوان أخرى
the theory predicts that every so often
تتنبأ هذه النظرية بأنه كل حين وآخر
those universes can collide.
يمكن لهذه الاكوان ان تتصادم
And if our universe got hit by another,
ولو تعرض كوننا للضرب بواسطة كون آخر
that collision
فسوف ينتج هذا التصادم
would generate an additional subtle pattern
شكلاً اضافياً رقيقاً
of temperature variations across space
من التغير الحراري عبر الفضاء
that we might one day
من الممكن يوماً ما
be able to detect.
ان نتمكن من اكتشافه
And so exotic as this picture is,
ومثل غرابة هذه الصورة
it may one day be grounded
من المحتمل ان تكون يوماً ما
in observations,
مرتكزة على الملاحظات
establishing the existence of other universes.
التي تتبنى وجود اكوان اخرى
I'll conclude
سوف الخص
with a striking implication
مع التضمين المدهش
of all these ideas
لكل هذه الافكار
for the very far future.
للمستقبل البعيد جداً
You see, we learned
كما ترون ، لقد تعلمنا
that our universe is not static,
ان كوننا ليس ساكناً
that space is expanding,
و ان الفضاء يتمدد
that that expansion is speeding up
وان ذلك التمدد يتسارع
and that there might be other universes
وانه من المحتمل وجود اكوان اخرى
all by carefully examining
كلها بالاختبار المتأني
faint pinpoints of starlight
لضوء نجم متناهي في الصغر
coming to us from distant galaxies.
يأتينا من المجرات البعيدة
But because the expansion is speeding up,
ولكن لأن التمدد يتسارع
in the very far future,
في المستقبل البعيد جداً
those galaxies will rush away so far and so fast
ستتباعد هذه المجرات بعيداً وبصورة سريعة
that we won't be able to see them --
بحيث لا نتمكن من رؤيتها
not because of technological limitations,
ليس بسبب محدودية تقنياتنا
but because of the laws of physics.
ولكن بسبب قوانين الفيزياء
The light those galaxies emit,
الضوء التي تبعثه هذه المجرات
even traveling at the fastest speed, the speed of light,
يسافر بسرعة أعلى من سرعة الضوء
will not be able to overcome
لن نتمكن من التغلب على
the ever-widening gulf between us.
اتساع الفجوة بيننا
So astronomers in the far future
لذا فان الفلكيين في المستقبل البعيد
looking out into deep space
ينظرون الى الفضاء العميق
will see nothing but an endless stretch
لن يروا شيئاً غير السلسلة اللامتناهية
of static, inky, black stillness.
من السكون ، الحبري الأسود
And they will conclude
وسوف يخلصون
that the universe is static and unchanging
الى ان الكون ساكن ولا يتغير
and populated by a single central oasis of matter
ويمتلئ بواحة مركزية وحيدة من المادة
that they inhabit --
التي تسكن
a picture of the cosmos
صورة من الاكوان
that we definitively know to be wrong.
التي بالتأكيد نعلم انه خطأ
Now maybe those future astronomers will have records
الآن من المحتمل ان يكون لدى فلكيي المستقبل سجلات
handed down from an earlier era,
تم تداولها من عصر سابق
like ours,
مثلنا
attesting to an expanding cosmos
تثبت التمدد الكوني
teeming with galaxies.
تعج بالمجرات
But would those future astronomers
ولكن هل سيصدق هؤلاء الفلكيون المستقبليون
believe such ancient knowledge?
بمثل هذه المعلومات القديمة؟
Or would they believe
او هل سيعتقدون
in the black, static empty universe
في الكون الأسود الساكن الفارغ
that their own state-of-the-art observations reveal?
الذي كشفت عنه مشاهداتهم المتطورة؟
I suspect the latter.
أشكّ بأنه الخيار الثاني
Which means that we are living
بما يعني اننا نعيش
through a remarkably privileged era
خلال عصر مميز بوضوح
when certain deep truths about the cosmos
عندما تكون هناك حقائق مؤكدة بعمق عن الاكوان
are still within reach
ما تزال في متناول الايدي
of the human spirit of exploration.
لروح البشر التائقة للإستكشاف
It appears that it may not always be that way.
يظهر انها لن تكون دوماً على هذا النسق
Because today's astronomers,
لأن فلكيو اليوم
by turning powerful telescopes to the sky,
بتوجيه تليسكوباتهم القوية الى السماء
have captured a handful of starkly informative photons --
قد التقطوا كمية من الفوتونات المليئة بالمعلومات الصارخة
a kind of cosmic telegram
نوعاً من البرقيات الكونية
billions of years in transit.
تستغرق بلايين السنوات في التنقل
and the message echoing across the ages is clear.
ويتردد صدى الرسالة عبر العصور بوضوح
Sometimes nature guards her secrets
احياناً تحرس الطبيعة اسرارها
with the unbreakable grip
بقبضة لا يمكن كسرها
of physical law.
من القوانين الفزيائية
Sometimes the true nature of reality beckons
أحياناً تومئ طبيعة الواقع
from just beyond the horizon.
من خلف الافق
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Brian, thank you.
كريس اندرسون: شكراً لك براين
The range of ideas you've just spoken about
كمية الافكار التي تحدثت عنها
are dizzying, exhilarating, incredible.
مدهشة و مبهجة ولا تصدق
How do you think
ماذا تعتقدون
of where cosmology is now,
عن مكان الكوزملوجي الان
in a sort of historical side?
من ناحية تاريخية نوعا ما
Are we in the middle of something unusual historically in your opinion?
هل نحن في وسط شيء غير معتاد تاريخياً من وجهة نظرنا
BG: Well it's hard to say.
بي جي: انه من الصعب القول
When we learn that astronomers of the far future
بانه عندما تعلمنا ان الفلكيين في المستقبل البعيد
may not have enough information to figure things out,
ليس لديهم معلومات كافية لمعرفة
the natural question is, maybe we're already in that position
السؤال الطبيعي هو ، من المحتمل ان نكون بالفعل في هذا الوضع
and certain deep, critical features of the universe
وبعمق معين ، فان ملامح حاسمة للكون
already have escaped our ability to understand
قد هربت قدرتنا على الفهم
because of how cosmology evolves.
بسبب كيفية تطور الكوزمولوجي
So from that perspective,
ومن هذا المنظور
maybe we will always be asking questions
يمكن دوما ان نسأل أسئلة
and never be able to fully answer them.
ولن نتمكن من الاجابة الكاملة عليها
On the other hand, we now can understand
على الجانب الآخر ، يمكننا الآن ان نفهم
how old the universe is.
كم عمر الكون
We can understand
يمكننا ان نفهم
how to understand the data from the microwave background radiation
كيفية فهم البيانات من الاشعة الخلفية للميكرويف
that was set down 13.72 billion years ago --
هذا تم تأريخه منذ 13.72 بليون عاماً
and yet, we can do calculations today to predict how it will look
وحتى الان ، يمكننا تنفيذ عمليات حسابية للتنبؤ عن ماذا سيكون شكله
and it matches.
وتم مطابقتها
Holy cow! That's just amazing.
هذا مذهل
So on the one hand, it's just incredible where we've gotten,
لذا في جهة ما ، انه فقط من غير المعقول ان ماحصلنا عليه
but who knows what sort of blocks we may find in the future.
ولكن من يعلم ما هو نوع المعوقات التي سنجدها في المستقبل
CA: You're going to be around for the next few days.
ك أ : ستكون في الجوار الايام القليلة المقبلة
Maybe some of these conversations can continue.
من المحتمل أن تستمر بعض من هذه النقاشات
Thank you. Thank you, Brian. (BG: My pleasure.)
شكرا لك ، شكرا لك براين. (ب جي : بكل سرور)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)